Finding Aid for Church of God in Michigan, General Assembly 1880-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Church of God in Michigan. General Assembly records 1880-1988
Church of God in Michigan. General Assembly records
Governing body of the Church of God denomination in Michigan. Administrative records, 1925-1988, including annual reports, minutes of Michigan Ministerial Assembly, and minutes and reports of various church committees, divisions, and boards; correspondence with various individual congregations, also collected historical materials about specific congregations; correspondence of executive secretary-treasurer Gale Hetrick; correspondence files of other clergy and church officials; historical materials collected by Hetrick as background for his history of the church; audio-tapes; and photographs.
89354 Ba 2, UBAl
17 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records (donor no. 7588 ) were received in 1988 from the church office through the Rev. Gerald Nevitt and Joyce Shriner.
The collection is open for research.
According to church historian Gale Hetrick, the first congregation of the Church of God reformation movement in Michigan met in the small community of Carson City in 1881. Participating in this meeting were Joseph C. Fisher, his wife Allie, and Daniel S. Warner (1842-1895), the individual acknowledged as the founder of what became the Church of God in Michigan.
Warner, a native of Marshallville, Ohio, was licensed in October 1867 by the Churches of God West Ohio Eldership, the religious communion established by Joseph Winebrenner in 1830. Sometime during the late 1870s, Warner became involved in the holiness movement, claiming the experience of sanctification in 1877. His preaching of holiness soon became intolerable to the Churches of God Eldership. As a result of charges brought against him, Warner's license to preach was withheld in January 1878. In October 1878, Warner joined the Northern Indiana Eldership of the Church of God, a splinter group of the Churches of God of North America. Warner's association with this group was an uneasy one and in 1881, first in Beaver Dam, Indiana, and then in Carson City, he established congregations of individuals who shared his belief in the theology of holiness and the doctrine of the oneness of Christians.
The history of the Church of God in Michigan has been chronicled in Gale Hetrick's book, Laughter Among the Trumpets (1980). The researcher should consult that volume for detailed discussion of the church's development. An important part of Warner's reformation and the means used to link the various individual congregations was the newspaper Gospel Trumpet (first published under that name in 1879). The significance of singing to the movement was underscored with the publication of the Songs of Victory songbook in 1885.
In the first decades of its existence, the Church of God of Michigan sought to meet the needs of its people for fellowship, indoctrination, inspiration, and cohesion through grove and camp meetings, and variously scheduled assemblies. After twenty years of flourishing, the camp meeting began a period of stagnation and decline. The leaders of the movement thereafter looked to the local congregation as the single most important grouping of believers.
As a movement, the Church of God was largely opposed to organization on a denominational level. In the early years, there were no elections, boards or committees. The result was extremely powerful, local, informal bishops. In 1920, believing the need for a special meeting of local ministers, apart from the General Assembly in Anderson, Indiana, the Michigan Ministerial Association was formed. Its purpose was to regulate and sanction clergy pastoring Church of God congregations, and also to resolve differences between congregations and pastors.
Further organizational change came in 1943 with the establishment of the Christian Service Board of the Church of God in Michigan, which was renamed in 1967 as the Board of Directors of the General Assembly of the Church of God in Michigan. The board was established to coordinate church activities within the state. In 1967, the church built an office facility for the purpose of housing and implementing the church's statewide programs.
The records of the Church of God in Michigan consist primarily of correspondence, administrative records, collected historical files, and photographs and audio-tapes, covering the period of 1880 to 1988. The bulk of the records date from 1920, the year of the founding of the Michigan Ministerial Assembly. In large part, the collection was collected and maintained by church historian and executive secretary, Gale Hetrick.
The collection divides into eleven series: Michigan Ministerial Assembly; Administrative Records; Congregational Records; Congregation Historical Materials; Executive Secretary-Treasurer, Gale Hetrick, Correspondence Files; Correspondence with Clergy and Church Officers; Church Organizational Files; Printed Material; Collected Historical Materials; Audio-tapes; and Photographs. The final two series, Audio-tapes and Photographs are unprocessed.
Subjects:
Church of God (Anderson, Ind.)--Michigan.; Church of God in Michigan. General Assembly.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Church of God (Anderson, Ind.)--Michigan.; Church of God in Michigan. General Assembly.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Michigan Mininsterial Assembly 1937-1957
  The Michigan Ministerial Assembly series consists of a record book of the yearly meetings for the years 1920-1942, and an account book of the Ministerial Convention for the period 1937-1957.
  - Record book 1920-1942 (Box 1)
  - Account book of the Ministerial Convention 1937-1957 (Box 1)
- Administrative Records 1925-1987
  Administrative Records covers the years 1925-1987. Arranged chronologically, these yearly file(s) consist of such materials as board of directors' meeting minutes, reports (staff and division), budget materials, and mailings to members. As expected, the files are more fulsome for the most recent period than they are for the first decade of the General Assembly's existence
  - Yearly File
    - 1925-1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965-1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981-1987 (Box 4)
- Congregational Records
  The Congregational Records and the Congregational Historical Materials series relate to the activities and histories of the congregations of the Church of God in Michigan. Congregational Records is alphabetically arranged by Michigan locale and consists of records maintained by the denomination. Included are records maintained by the secretary-treasurer of the denomination's State Board of Church Extension for the period of since the mid 1940s. Each file consists of correspondence with the local church, primarily concerning church building and local activities. Also included are the Monthly Reports that each local congregation filed with the General Assembly office and containing attendance and financial information.
  - Adrian (Box 4)
  - Ann Arbor (Box 4)
  - Avon (Box 4)
  - Allegan (Box 4)
  - Battle Creek (Box 4)
  - Beaverton (Box 4)
  - Benton Heights, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Big Rapids (Box 4)
  - Big Rapids Project (Box 4)
  - Boyne City (Box 4)
  - Buchanan (Box 4)
  - Burlington (Box 4)
  - Coldwater (Box 4)
  - Detroit-Greek Broadcast Project (Box 4)
  - Dollar Bay, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Dowagiac, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - East Jordan (Box 4)
  - Eaton Rapids (Box 4)
  - Edmore, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Higgins Lake (Box 5)
  - Hillsdale (Box 5)
  - Holbrook (Box 5)
  - Hope (Box 5)
  - Hudson (Box 5)
  - Ionia (Box 5)
  - Jackson-High Street (Box 5)
  - Kalamazoo-North Street (Box 5)
  - Kingsford (Box 5)
  - Lansing-West (Box 5)
  - Monroe (Box 5)
  - Monroe-State Highway Easement (Box 5)
  - Muskegon-East Muskegon (Box 5)
  - Muskegon (Box 5)
  - Muskegon Heights (Box 5)
  - Pentwater (Box 5)
  - Petoskey, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Pontiac-Eastside (Box 5)
  - Pontiace-Southside (bound ledger) (Box 5)
  - Portage (Box 5)
  - Port Huron, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Saginaw (Box 5)
  - Saint Louis (Box 5)
  - South Haven (Box 5)
  - Stanton (Box 5)
  - Traverse City, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Troy (Box 5)
  - Ypsilanti-Community (Box 5)
  - Ypsilanti-Congress Street (Box 5)
- Congregational Historical Materials
  Congregation Historical Materials is also arranged alphabetically by congregation. Unlike the Congregational Records series that was created by a division within the denomination, this one was probably created by Hetrick in the preparation of his book. The materials within each file vary, consisting of such items as church histories (published and manuscript), bylaws and constitution, church directories, programs, clippings, scrapbooks, and an occasional photograph or record book.
  - Adrian (Box 6)
  - Albion (Box 6)
  - Allegan (Box 6)
  - Alma (Box 6)
  - Alpena (Box 6)
  - Baroda (Box 6)
  - Barryton (Box 6)
  - Battle Creek (Box 6)
  - Bay City (Box 6)
  - Beaverton (Box 6)
  - Benton Harbor (Box 6)
  - Benton Heights (Box 6)
  - Big Rapids (Box 6)
  - Buchanan (Box 6)
  - Burlington (Box 6)
  - Burton (Box 6)
  - Cadillac (Box 6)
  - Cassopolis (Box 6)
  - Cedar Rapids (Box 6)
  - Charlevoix (Box 6)
  - Charlotte (Box 6)
  - Clare (Box 6)
  - Clio (Box 6)
  - Coldwater (Box 6)
  - Colon (Box 6)
  - Crystal (Box 6)
  - Decatur (Box 6)
  - Detroit
    - Bethany (Box 6)
    - Greek (Box 6)
    - Hendricks Street (Box 6)
    - Jay and Chene Streets (Box 6)
    - Joseph Campau Avenue (Box 6)
    - Metropolitan (Box 6)
    - Northwestern (Box 6)
    - Richmond (Box 6)
    - Southwestern (Box 6)
    - State Fair (Box 6)
    - West Hancock (Box 6)
    - Wisconsin (Box 6)
  - Dowagiac (Box 6)
  - Edmore (Box 6)
  - Edwarsdsburg (Box 6)
  - Flint
    - Dupont Street (Box 6)
    - First Church of God (Box 6)
    - Holbrook Avenue (Box 6)
    - Twelfth Street (Box 6)
    - West Court Street (Box 6)
    - Westwood (Box 6)
  - Frederic (Box 6)
  - Grand Junction (Box 6)
  - Grand Rapids (Box 6)
  - Greenville (Box 6)
  - Hillsdale (Box 6)
  - Hope (Box 6)
  - Howell (Box 6)
  - Ithaca (Box 6)
  - Jackson (Box 6)
  - Kalamazoo (Box 6)
  - Kawkawlin (Box 6)
  - Laingsburg (Box 6)
  - Lansing
    - Jenison Street (Box 6)
    - Pennway (Box 6)
    - South Street (Box 6)
    - West Lansing (Box 6)
  - Lincoln Park (Box 6)
  - Livonia (Box 6)
  - Marshall (Box 6)
  - Mesick (Box 6)
  - Midland (Box 6)
  - Mio (Box 6)
  - Monroe (Box 6)
  - Mount Clemens (Box 6)
  - Mount Haley (Box 6)
  - Mount Pleasant (Box 6)
  - Muskegon (Box 6)
  - Niles (Box 6)
  - North Bradley (Box 6)
  - Otsego (Box 6)
  - Owosso (Box 6)
  - Plymouth (Box 6)
  - Pontiac (Box 6)
  - Portage (Box 6)
  - Port Huron (Box 6)
  - Romeo (Box 6)
  - Royal Oak (Box 6)
  - Saginaw (Box 6)
  - Saint Johns (Box 6)
  - Saint Joseph (Box 6)
  - Saint Louis (Box 6)
  - Sanford (Box 6)
  - Sears (Box 6)
  - South Haven (Box 6)
  - Sterling Heights (Box 6)
  - Sturgis (Box 6)
  - Swartz Creek (Box 6)
  - Three Rivers (Box 6)
  - Traverse City (Box 6)
  - Troy (Box 6)
  - Wyoming (Box 6)
  - Ypsilanti (Box 6)
- Executive Secretary-Treasurer: Gale Hetrick 1951-1981
  Executive Secretary-Treasurer Gale Hetrick series consists of outgoing correspondence for the years 1961-1969, and incoming correspondence for the years 1952-1981 (scattered).
  - Outgoing correspondence 1961-1969 (Box 7)
  - Incoming correspondence 1952-1981 (scattered dates) (Box 8)
- Correspondence 1930-1980
  Correspondence (primarily with clergy and church officials), as the name implies, is a series of alphabetically- arranged correspondence covering the period from the early 1930s to 1980. Major portions include correspondence of John W. Batdorf, who was chairman of the denomination's pastoral relations committee; and correspondence of P.V. Jacobs, a missionary in South India. Correspondence here sometimes relates to matters of pastoral relations and questions about doctrinal positions of individual pastors.
  - Batdorf, John W. 1934-1944, 9 folders (Box 9)
  - Burgess, Emma 1932-1936, 6 folders (Box 9)
  - Clingenpeel, George H. 1933-1959 (Box 9)
  - De Puit, Don 1948-1953 (Box 9)
  - Eldridge, William 1935 (Box 9)
  - Gray, William A.,1935 (Box 9)
  - Hargett, N.G. 1948-1956, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Jacob, P.V. 1966-1979, 9 folders (Box 9)
  - Kilpatrick, Ira N. 1934-1937 (Box 9)
  - Kupisch, Vance 1965-1967 (Box 9)
  - Lane, W.F. 1948 (Box 9)
  - Masey, James 1935 (Box 9)
  - Mauch, Maurice J. 1961-1962 (Box 9)
  - Miller, T. Franklin 1957-1958 (Box 9)
  - Pontions, Elry 1934-1937 (Box 9)
  - Raab, Mary 1962 (Box 9)
  - Reedy, E. N. 1932-1934, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Schroeder, William T. 1934-1954 (Box 9)
  - Shockley, Richard W. 1979-1980 (Box 9)
  - Sickal, Dorothy 1957-1960 (Box 9)
  - Sickal, W. Lee 1958 (Box 9)
  - Tuttle, Raymond J. 1947-1956, 5 folders (Box 9)
  - Warner, Daniel S. 1892 (facsimile) (Box 9)
- Church Organizations circa 1940-1985
  Church Organizations is arranged alphabetically by the name of divisions or boards within the denomination. It covers the period of approximately 1940 to the early 1980s, though there are some scattered items on either side of those dates. Among the units represented in this series are the Christian Education Division, the Christian Service Board, the Church Extension Board, Men of the Church of God, Minutemen, Michigan Youth Fellowship Committee, and various other youth, women's, and men's groups.
  - Associations in Christian Education, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Care Lab Conference 1973 (Box 10)
  - Centennial Committee minutes 1979 (Box 10)
  - Christian Education, Board of 1933, 1938, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Christian Education Division
    - Minutes 1964-1981, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - "Operation Mobilization" circa 1971 (Box 10)
  - Christian Service Board
    - Minutes 1944-1965 (Box 10)
    - Bylaws (Box 10)
    - Financial records 1948-1963, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Church Extension Board
    - Minutes 1940-1963, 1965-1979, 4 volumes; 6 folders (Box 10)
    - Financial records 1967-1972 (Box 10)
    - General correspondence
      - 1943-1944 (Box 10)
      - 1961-1972 (Box 10)
  - Conference on Christian Ministries 1962-1969, 1971, 1976, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Continuing Education Committee minutes 1977-1980 (Box 11)
  - Harvest Offering 1973, 1975-1977 (Box 11)
  - Kingdom Builders 1975 (Box 11)
  - Men of the Church of God
    - Minutes 1967, 1969-1977, 1981, 8 folders (Box 11)
  - Michigan Board of Christian Education
    - Minutes 1940-1967, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Michigan Laboratory School
    - General correspondence 1957-1961 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Million Campaign
    - Financial report 1946 (Box 11)
  - Michigan State Evangelism Committee
    - Minutes and financial report 1928, 1937 (Box 11)
  - Michigan Woman's Missionary Society
    - Minutes 1960-1975 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Mid-Century Advance Committee
    - General correspondence 1948, 1950 (Box 11)
  - Ministers Wives Conference
    - Minutes 1955-1963 (Box 11)
  - Minutemen
    - Minutes 1960-1967, 7 folders (Box 11)
  - Personnel Committee
    - Minutes 1972, 1975 (Box 11)
  - Program Committee
    - Minutes 1975, 1976, 1981 (Box 11)
  - Retreats and Planning Committee 1960-1961 (Box 11)
  - Saint Louis Camp Meeting
    - Board minutes 1961-1977 (scattered) (Box 11)
  - Study Commission minutes 1957, 1959 (Box 11)
  - Search Committee
    - Minutes 1979-1981 (Box 11)
  - Social Concerns Division (Box 12)
    - Minutes 1964-1981 (Box 12)
  - State Leader's Camp 1949-1951, 1959 (Box 12)
  - Women of the Church of God
    - Minutes and directory 1975 (Box 12)
    - General correspondence 1975-1977 (Box 12)
  - World Service
    - General correspondence 1960-1979 (scattered) (Box 12)
  - Youth organizations
    - Hands Across Michigan (H.A.M.) 1963-1965 (Box 12)
    - Michigan Youth Fellowship Committee
      - Minutes 1960-1981 (Box 12)
      - Agenda for meetings 1963, 1965-1967 (Box 12)
      - Caravans 1963-1965 (Box 12)
      - Conference leaders 1967 (Box 12)
      - District Representatives 1963-1965 (Box 12)
      - Monies and financial reports 1960-1967 (Box 12)
      - Scholarships 1963, 1965-1968 (Box 12)
      - Workcamps 1963 (Box 12)
    - State Youth Convention
      - Minutes 1956-1970 (Box 12)
      - Minutes 1972-1976 (Box 12)
    - Youth Camp
      - Minutes 1979 (Box 12)
      - Camp director's reports 1979 (Box 12)
      - Financial statements 1949, 1951 (Box 12)
      - Planning 1977 197 (Box 12)
      - Rainbow Lake (staff resource book) (Box 12)
      - Study Committee minutes (Box 12)
      - Working File 1977-1980 (Box 12)
    - Youth Division
      - Annual report 1968-1969 (Box 12)
      - Minutes 1977-1981 (Box 12)
- Printed Material 1944-1988
  Printed Material includes copies of Michigan Bulletin, 1944-1988 (many issues missing); and various programs from church conventions. Collected Historical Materials consists of notes made and copies of documents collected by Gale Hetrick as preparation for his book Laughter Among the Trumpets.
  - Michigan Bulletin 1944-1988, 16 folders (Box 13)
    (many issues missing)
  - Christian Education Convention
    - 1948-1949 (Box 13)
    - 1959-1960 (Box 13)
  - State Ministerial/General Assembly programs 1921-1977 (scattered) (Box 13)
  - State Sunday School Convention
    - Programs 1946-1955 (Box 13)
  - State Youth Convention
    - Programs 1924-1971 (scattered) (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
- Collected Historical Material
  - Gale Hetrick files and notes
    - Alma College conference (Box 14)
    - Burlington Camp meeting excerpts (Box 14)
    - Byrum (N.H.) and Gospel Trumpet (Box 14)
    - Byrum (N.H.) diary excerpts (Box 14)
    - Christian Service Board history (Box 14)
    - Correspondence (Box 14)
    - Durkelberger, Emma Martha (Box 14)
    - Kalamazoo tapes (Box 14)
    - Laughter Among the Trumpets (drafts) (Box 14)
    - Massey, James: The Church in Relation to the Negro (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
    - Oden, Daniel Felix (Box 14)
    - Paddleford, Christie (Box 14)
    - Perry, Estel (Box 14)
    - Perry, Ocie (Box 14)
    - Sheldon, Leroy (Box 14)
    - Sweet, Verna (Box 14)
    - Warner, Daniel Sidney (Box 14)
    - Weeks, Helen (Box 14)
    - Williamston 1884-1886 (Box 14)
  - Published, etc
    - Anthems from the Throne by D.S. and B.E. Warner (Gospel Trumpet Publishing Company, Grand Junction, Michigan, 1888) (Box 14)
    - Batdorf, John (Box 14)
    - Byrum, E.E (Box 14)
    - Dunkelberger, Emma Martha (photocopied excerpts from autograph book 1895, 1900 (Box 14)
    - Familiar Names and Faces by N.H. Byrum (Gospel Trumpet Publishing Company, Moundsville, West Virginia, 1902) (Box 14)
    - Gospel Trumpet Publishing Work Described Illustrated by A.L. Byers (Gospel Trumpet Publishing Company ?, Anderson, Indiana, 1907) (Box 14)
    - Grover, W.B., "Children's Home and School" ledger circa 1898-1910 (Box 14)
    - Hetrick, Gale (Box 14)
    - Massey, James
      - Essays: Raymond S. Jackson, Daniel F. Oden, J.D. Smoot (Box 14)
    - Michels, Sebastian (Box 14)
    - Noble, Louis A
      - Diary excerpts 1893 (photocopy) (Box 14)
      - Diary excerpts 1893 (typescript) (Box 14)
      - Autograph book excerpts 1892-1898 (Box 14)
        (photocopies)
      - Gospel Trumpet family list December 1, 1893 (Box 14)
    - Oden, Daniel Felix
      - Sheldon, Leroy (Box 14)
      - Scripture notebooks 1898, 2 volumes (Box 14)
    - Smock, Gary Albert (Box 14)
    - Songs of the Evening Light by Barney E. Warren and Andrew L. Byers (Gospel Trumpet Publishing Company, Grand Junction, Michigan, 1897) (Box 14)
    - State Headquarters Building (clipping) (Box 14)
- Audio-tapes
  - Audiotapes (unprocessed) (Box 15)
- Photographs
  - Photographs (unprocessed) (Box 16)
  - Photographs (unprocessed) (Box 17)
    (continued)
  - Photographs (Folder UBAl)